part 1 chapter 3.
Winston was dreaming of his mother.
He must, he thought of been 10 or 11 years old when his mother had disappeared.
She was a tall, statuesque, rather silent woman with slow movements and magnificent fair hair.
His father he remembered more vaguely as dark and thin, dressed always in neat dark clothes
(Winston remembered especially the very thin soles of his father's shoes) and
wearing spectacles.
The two of them must evidently have been swallowed up in one of the first great
purges of the 50s At this moment his mother was sitting in
some place deep down beneath him, with his young sister in her arms.
He did not remember his sister at all, except as a tiny, feeble baby, always
silent, with large, watchful eyes.
Both of them were looking up at him.
They were down in some subterranean place— —the bottom of a well, for instance,
or a very deep grave— —but it was a place which, already far
below him, was itself moving downwards.
They were in the saloon of a sinking ship, looking up at him through the darkening water.
There was still air in the saloon, they could still see him and he them, but all
the while they were sinking down, down into the green waters which in another
moment must hide them from sight forever He was out in the light and air while
they were being sucked down to death, and they were down there because he was up here.
He knew it and they knew it, and he could see the knowledge in their faces. There
was no reproach either in their faces or in their hearts,
only the knowledge that they must die in order that he might remain alive, and
that this was part of the unavoidable order of things.
He could not remember what had happened, but he knew in his dream that in some
way the lives of his mother and his sister had been sacrificed to his own.
It was one of those dreams which, while retaining the characteristic dream
scenery, are a continuation of one's intellectual life, and in which one
becomes aware of facts and ideas which still seem new and valuable after one is awake.
The thing that now suddenly struck Winston was that his mother's death,
nearly 30 years ago, had been tragic and sorrowful in a way that was no longer possible.
Tragedy, he perceived, belonged to the ancient time, to a time when there was
still privacy, love and friendship, and when the members of a family stood by
one another without needing to know the reason.
His mother's memory tore at his heart because she had died loving him, when he
was too young and selfish to love her in return, and because somehow, he did not
remember how, she had sacrificed herself to a conception of loyalty that was
private and unalterable.
Such things, he saw, could not happen today. Today there were fear, hatred and
pain, but no dignity of emotion, no deep or complex sorrows.
All this he seemed to see in the large eyes of his mother and his sister,
looking up at him through the green water, hundreds of fathoms down and still sinking.
Suddenly he was standing on short springy turf, on a summer evening when
the slanting rays of the sun gilded the ground.
The landscape that he was looking at recurred so often in his dreams that he
was never fully certain whether or not he had seen it in the real world.
In his waking thoughts he called it the Golden Country.
It was an old rabbit bitten pasture, with a foot track wandering across it and a
molehill here and there.
In the ragged hedge on the opposite side of the field the bowels of the elm trees
were swaying very faintly in the breeze, their leaves just stirring in dense
masses like women's hair.
Somewhere near at hand, though out of sight, there was a clear, slow-moving
stream where dace was swimming in the pools under the willow trees.
The girl with dark hair was coming towards them across the field.
With what seemed a single movement she tore off her clothes and flung them disdainfully aside.
Her body was white and smooth, but it aroused no desire in him, indeed he
barely looked at it. What overwhelmed him in that instant was admiration for the
gesture with which she had thrown her clothes aside.
With its grace and carelessness it seemed to annihilate a whole culture, a
whole system of thought, as though Big Brother and the Party and the Thought
Police could all be swept into nothingness by a single splendid movement of the arm.
That too was a gesture belonging to the ancient time.
Winston woke up with the word 'Shakespeare' on his lips.
The telescreen was giving forth an ear splitting whistle which continued on the
same note for 30 seconds.
It was North 715 getting up time for office workers.
Winston wrenched his body out of bed— —naked, for a member of the Outer Party
received only 3 000 clothing coupons annually, and a suit of pajamas was 600.
and seized the dingy singlet and a pair of shorts that were lying across a chair.
The Physical jokes would begin in three minutes.
The next moment he was doubled up by a violent coughing fit which nearly always
attacked him soon after waking up. It emptied his lungs so completely that he
could only begin breathing again by lying on his back and taking a series of deep gasps.
His veins had swelled with the effort of the cough, and the varicus also had started itching
30 to 40 group!' yapped a piercing female voice 30 to 40 group! Take your places,
please 30s to 40s Winston sprang to a tension in front of
the telescreen, upon which the image of a youngish woman, scrawny but muscular,
dressed in tunic and gym shoes had already appeared.
'Arms bending and stretching!' she wrapped out. 'Take your time by me. One, two, three,
four! One, two, three, four! Come on, comrades, put a bit of life into it! One, two, three,
four! One, two, three, four!...'
The pain of the coughing fitted not quite driven out of Winston's mind the
impression made by his dream, and the rhythmic movements of the exercise restored it somewhat.
As he mechanically shot his arms back and forth, wearing on his face the look
of grim enjoyment which was considered proper during the Physical Jerks, he was
struggling to think his way backward into the dim period of his early childhood.
It was extraordinarily difficult.
Beyond the late 50s everything faded.
When there were no external records that you could refer to, even the outline of
your own life lost its sharpness.
You remembered huge events which had quite probably not happened, you
remembered the detail of incidents without being able to recapture their
atmosphere, and there were long blank periods to which you could assign nothing
had been different then.
Even the names of countries, and their shapes on the map, had been different.
Airstrip One, for instance, had not been so called in those days: it had been
called England or Britain, though London, he felt fairly certain, had always been called London.
Winston could not definitely remember a time when his country had not been at
war, but it was evident that there had been a fairly long interval of peace
during his childhood, because one of his early memories was of an air raid which
appeared to take everyone by surprise.
Perhaps it was the time when the atomic bomb had fallen on Colchester.
He did not remember the raid itself, but he did remember his father's hand
clutching his own as they hurried down, down, down into some place deep in the
earth, round and round a spiral staircase which rang under his feet and which
finally so wearied his legs that he began whimpering and they had to stop and rest.
His mother, in her slow dreamy way, was following a long way behind them.
She was carrying his baby's sister— —or perhaps it was only a bundle of blankets
that she was carrying: he was not certain whether his sister had been born then.
Finally they had emerged into a noisy, crowded place which he had realized to be a Tube station.
There were people sitting all over the stone flagged floor, and other people,
packed tightly together, were sitting on metal bunks, one above the other.
Winston and his mother and father found themselves a place on the floor, and near
them an old man and an old woman was sitting side by side on a bunk.
The old man had on a decent dark suit and a black cloth cap pushed back from
very white hair: his face was scarlet and his eyes were
blue and full of tears. He reeked of Jinn It seemed to breathe out of his skin in
place of sweat, and one could have fancied that the tears wailing from his eyes were pure gin.
But those slightly drunk he was also suffering under some grief that was genuine and unbearable.
In his childish way Winston grasped that some terrible thing, something that was
beyond forgiveness and could never be remedied, had just happened.
It also seemed to him that he knew what it was.
Someone whom the old man loved, a little granddaughter perhaps, had been killed.
Every few minutes the old man kept repeating: 'We didn't ought to have trusted him I
said so, Ma, didn't I?
That's what comes of trusting him I said so all along.
We didn't ought to have trusted the buggers.'
But which buggers they didn't ought to have trusted Winston could not now remember.
Since about that time, war had been literally continuous so strictly
speaking it had not always been the same war.
For several months during his childhood that had been confused street fighting
in London itself, some of which he remembered vividly.
But to trace out the history of the whole period, to say who was fighting
whom at any given moment, would have been utterly impossible, since no written
record, and no spoken word, ever made mention of any other alignment than the existing one.
At this moment, for example, in 1984 (if it was 1984), Oceania was at war with Eurasia
and in alliance with East Asia In no public or private utterance was it
ever admitted that the three powers had at any time been grouped along different lines.
Actually, as Winston well knew, it was only four years since Oceania had been
at war with East Asia and in alliance with Eurasia.
But that was merely a piece of furtive knowledge which he happened to possess
because his memory was not satisfactorily under control.
Officially the change of partners had never happened.
Oceania was at war with Eurasia: therefore Oceania had always been at war with Eurasia.
The enemy of the moment always represented absolute evil, and it
followed that any past or future agreement with him was impossible.
The frightening thing, he reflected for the ten thousandth time as he forced his
shoulders painfully backward (with hands on hips, they were gyrating their bodies
from the waist, an exercise that was supposed to be good for the back muscles)—
)—the frightening thing was that it might all be true.
If the Party could thrust its hand into the past and say of this or that event,
it never happened— —that, surely, was more terrifying than mere torture and death?
The Party said that Oceania had never been in alliance with Eurasia.
He, Winston Smith, knew that Oceania had been an alliance with Eurasia as shorter
time as four years ago.
But where did that knowledge exist?
Only in his own consciousness, which in any case must soon be annihilated.
And if all others accepted the lie which the part he imposed— —if all records told
the same tale— —then the lie passed into history and became truth.
'Who controls the past,' ran the Party slogan, 'controls the future: who controls
the present controls the past.'
And yet the past, though of its nature alterable, never had been altered.
Whatever was true now was true from everlasting to everlasting.
It was quite simple.
All that was needed was an unending series of victories over your own memory.
'Reality control', they called it: in Newspeak, 'doublethink'.
'Stand easy!' barked the instructors a little more genially.
Winston sank his arms to his sides and slowly refilled his lungs with air.
His mind slid away into the labyrinthine world of doublethink.
To know and not to know, to be conscious of complete truthfulness while telling
carefully constructed lies, to hold simultaneously two opinions which
canceled out, knowing them to be contradictory and believing in both of them;
to use logic against logic, to repudiate morality while laying claim to it, to
believe that the democracy was impossible and that the Party was the
guardian of democracy; to forget whatever it was necessary to forget, then to draw
it back into memory again at the moment when it was needed, and then promptly to
forget it again: and above all, to apply the same process to the process itself.
That was the ultimate subtlety: consciously to induce unconsciousness,
and then, once again, to become unconscious of the act of hypnosis you had just performed.
Even to understand the word double think involved the use of doublethink.
The instructors had called them to attention again.
'And now let's see which of us can touch our toes!' she said enthusiastically. 'Right
over from the hips, please, comrades one two one do Winston loathed this exercise, which sent
shooting pains all the way from his heels to his buttocks and often ended by
bringing on another coughing fit.
The half Pleasant quality went out of his meditations.
The past, he reflected, had not merely been altered, it had actually been destroyed.
For how could you establish even the most obvious fact when there existed no
record outside your own memory?
He tried to remember in what year he had first heard mention of Big Brother.
He thought it must have been at some time in the 60s but it was impossible to
be certain.
In the Party histories, of course, Big Brother figured as the leader and
guardian of the Revolution since its very earliest days.
His exploits had been gradually pushed backwards in time until already they
extended into the fabulous world of the 40s and the 30s when the capitalists in
their strange cylindrical hats still rode through the streets of London in
great gleaming Motorcars or horse carriages with glass sides.
There was no knowing how much of this legend was true and how much invented.
Winston could not even remember at what date the Party itself had come into existence.
He did not believe he had ever heard the word insock before 1960.
it was possible that in its old speak form—' —'English Socialism', that is to say— —it
had been current earlier.
Everything melted into mist.
Sometimes indeed, you could put your finger on a definite lie. It was not true,
for example, as was claimed in the Party history books, that the Party had invented airplanes
He remembered airplanes since his earliest childhood.
But you could prove nothing.
There was never any evidence.
Just once in his whole life he had held in his hands unmistakable documentary
proof of the falsification of an historical fact.
And on that occasion— 'Smith!' screamed the shrewish voice from the telescreen.
'6079 Smith W! Yes, you! Bend lower, please!
You can do better than that. You're not trying. Lower, please!
That's better, comrade.
Now stand at ease, the whole squad, and watch me.'
A sudden hot sweat had broken out all over Winston's body.
His face remains completely inscrutable.
Never show dismay! Never show resentment!
A single flicker of the eyes could give you away.
He stood watching while the instructors raised her arms above her head and— —one
could not say gracefully, but with remarkable neatness and efficiency— —bent
over and tucked the first joint of her fingers under her toes.
'There, comrades! That's how I want to see you doing it. Watch me again. I'm 39 and
I've had four children.
Now look.'
She bent over again. 'You see my knees aren't bent. You can all do it if you
want to,' she added as she straightened herself up. 'Anyone under 45 is perfectly
capable of touching his toes.
We don't all have the privilege of fighting in the front line, but at least
we can all keep fit.
Remember our boys on the Malabar front!
And the sailors in the Floating Fortresses! Just think what they have to
put up with. Now try again. That's better comrade, that's much better,' she added
encouragingly as Winston, with a violent lunge, succeeded in touching his toes
with knees unbent, for the first time in several years